Finding Aid for Charles Trowbridge papers, ca. 1823-ca. 1840
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
C.C. Trowbridge papers ca. 1823-ca. 1840
Trowbridge, C. C. (Charles Christopher), 1800-1883.
0.5 linear ft.
86143 Aa 2
Clerk to Gen. Lewis Cass on 1819 expedition among Indians of upper Great Lakes, Indian agent and negotiator, mayor of Detroit in 1834, and later University of Michigan regent. Papers consist primarily of material relating to his early experience among the Indians including reports to Cass and other accounts of Indian life and language. Consists in part of photostats of material held by the Burton Historical Library.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. William Mitchell, daughter of Sydney Trowbridge Miller and came to the library in 1938. Donor no. 1764
The collection is open for research.
Charles Christopher Trowbridge was born in Albany, New York, December 29, 1800. He moved westward to Detroit in 1819 and shortly thereafter joined General Lewis Cass as a clerk and assistant topographer in Cass' expedition among the Indian tribes of the upper Great Lakes and Mississippi River. The purpose of the expedition was partly scientific and partly to improve relations with the Indian tribes of the area. In 1821, Secretary of War Calhoun appointed Trowbridge as Indian agent with responsibility of accompanying chiefs and representatives of the Six Nations of New York state to Green Bay for the purpose of finding suitable lands where the Six Nations might resettle. As an agent and Indian negotiator, Trowbridge was becoming increasing proficient in the study of tribal dialects and the customs and traditions of the Indians of the area. With his acknowledged expertise on Indian affairs, Trowbridge was given further and varied assignments as Indian agent, translator and mediator.
In 1825, Trowbridge began increasingly to devote himself to business pursuits such as banking, land development and sawmills. He also turned to politics, serving as mayor of Detroit in 1834 and running unsuccessfully for governor in 1837. Following Trowbridge's defeat, Governor Stevens T. Mason appointed him regent of the University of Michigan, where he served from 1839 until 1842. Business and civic pursuits engaged Trowbridge for the remainder of his life. He died April 3, 1883.
Further biographical information about Trowbridge will be found in James V. Campbell, "Biographical Sketch of Charles Christopher Trowbridge," Michigan Pioneer Coll., 6: 478-91; in Trowbridge's autobiography, Personal memoirs of Charles Christopher Trowbridge as written for his kindred (Detroit: 1893); and The territorial papers of the United States: Vol. XI, The Territory of Michigan, 1820-1829, p. 936.
The Trowbridge collection consists mainly of materials accumulated during the early years of his career when he was acting as Indian agent and when he devoted himself to the study of the languages and customs of the native Americans of the upper midwest.
The major portion of the Trowbridge papers are located at the Burton Historical Collection (NUCMC 70-1194)
Subjects:
Trowbridge, C. C. (Charles Christopher), 1800-1883.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); University of Michigan--History.
Contributors:
Higginson, Francis John, 1804-1872.
- Native American material
  - Response to Governor Lewis Cass' questionnaire concerning the Chippewa, Ottawa, and Winnebago Indians (Box 1)
    (photocopies in part; a portion of these manuscripts are located at the Burton Historical Collection)
  - Portion of a journal kept at Sault Ste. Marie, June 14-August 2, 1830 (?) (Box 1)
  - Speeches; folder includes:
    - Speech of Aukkebuggecaash (Gueule Plat) of Leech Lake, Upper Mississippi, delivered at the agency of Sault Ste. Marie, July 1830 (Box 1)
    - Speech of the Buffalo chief, Peezhikee, alias Way Ishkee, of Lapointe, Lake Superior, delivered at the agency of Sault Ste. Marie, July 1830 (Box 1)
  - Account of some of the traditions, manner, and customs of the Lenee Lenaupee, or Delaware Indians (37 pp.) (Box 1)
  - Traditions of the Lenee Lenaupee, or Delaware (27 pp.). (Box 1)
    (Appears to be an earlier draft of the manuscript)
  - Delaware language
    - Part I, a grammar (284 p.) (Box 1)
    - Part II, verb conjugations (Box 1)
    - Part I (Box 1)
      (apparently an earlier draft of the first 45 pages of Part I; these 48 pages compare very closely, with only minor differences, with the first 45 pages of the fuller version)
  - Traditions, manners, and customs of the Twaatwaa or Meearmeear Indians. (Box 1)
    (This manuscript is a slightly different version from that found at the Burton Historical Collection which was published as Meearmeear Traditions, edited by Vernon Kinietz in Occasional contributions from the Museum of Anthropology of the University of Michigan, no. 7, April 1938)
  - Keekarpoo Indians (2 versions) (Box 1)
  - Shauwanoa traditions, July 24, 1824 (Box 1)
    (This manuscript, based on information from the Prophet, was published, along with Black Hoofs account, in Shawnese Traditions, edited by Vernon Kinietz and Erminie W. Vogelin in Occasional contributions from the Museum of Anthropology of the University of Michigan, no. 9, June 1939)
  - Shauwonoa Traditions, Black Hoof's account of (Box 1)
  - Minneehoohauh Woahpee, 1823 (Box 1)
    (an incomplete dictionary of English terms translated into the Weannebeago, Dahcoatah, Munoamoanee, and Ojibwa languages)
  - Letters and speech giving information about the early history of the of the University of Michigan (Box 1)
    (Photostats of materials held by the Burton Historical Collection)